welcome welcome to meditating with John
Breaux Vicki I'm a cognitive
psychologist and a cognitive scientists
at the University of Toronto I'm also
the author of the awakening from the
meeting crisis series on YouTube I study
mindfulness scientifically I study
related phenomena like flow altered
states of consciousness mystical
experiences and wisdom in addition to
that scientific study of mindfulness
related phenomena I also have been
practicing the past nough and that Tai
Chi Chuan and Chi cung for 29 years I've
been teaching a course on Metta
contemplation the Pastner meditation and
also a course on Tai Chi Chuan for the
multi-faith centre at the University of
Toronto for the past 15 years so I'm
going to be teaching you what I was
taught I was taught an ecology of
practices I was taught of the past of
meditation and a meta contemplation and
Tai Chi Chuan I said she come and I'm
also going to be integrating that with
what I've learned about mindfulness from
my scientific investigation so normally
what will happen is there'll be a
teaching class on Mondays and a teaching
class on Thursdays today's an exception
where we're repeating the first video
from Monday because we had some
technical difficulties with the sound so
for those of you who saw it with me
yesterday I apologize for the repetition
that many of you requested better sound
so we're going to redo yesterday today
so please get in a comfortable position
hopefully you have some comfortable
clothing on please put your phones on
silent mode a couple of brief
announcements there'll be a Q&A section
at the end of this please limit your
questions to questions around this
practice and what I'm going to be
teaching you in this course if you have
more general Q&A for me I refer you to
the monthly Q&A we do every third Friday
unfortunately for the
month the monthly Q&A is cancelled due
to the disruption caused by the virus we
should be able to pick it up in a purely
virtual manner next month all right so
I'd like to begin with you now and I'd
like to begin with a central metaphor
for doing this practice it was a it's a
metaphor that comes from Satara Gotama
mmm I'm not trying to convert you to
Buddhism and I've already indicated I am
doing an ecology of practices some of
which are drawn from the Buddhist
tradition some from the Taoist tradition
and some from a secular scientific
framework but nevertheless the Buddha is
a very valuable resource that we should
make use of the buddha buddha pointed
out that the attitude you should take in
a meditative practice is you're trying
to befriend yourself you're trying to
learn how to take the relationship to
yourself that you would take to somebody
that you are cultivating a deep
friendship with so i'm going to teach
you how to come into how to begin to
come into that proper relationship to
yourself and i'm going to teach you what
i call the core for for coming into that
proper relationship of offending
yourself i'm finding your Center
finding your root finding it flow and
finding your focus so that's we're gonna
work on first so as I said normally
Mondays and Thursdays we'll type a
teaching class those are on 40 minutes
Tuesdays Wednesdays Fridays and Saturday
you can meet me here again at 9:30 but
those will only be half an hour and
those will be just a sitting I'll do a
brief reminder of what we've learned
we'll sit and then they'll be a Q&A so
we're friending yourself by finding your
Center so what does that mean one of the
oldest meditation manuals we have is in
fact translated as centering and people
often say they want to find their Center
but we need to move beyond sort of a
cliche we need to get into the depths of
what this can mean for us and so one of
the things you can think about is the
relationship between mind and body one
of the ways we can be friend our selves
is to get the proper relationship
between mind and body now often they're
there they're not communicating properly
and they may even have an up to an
antagonistic relationship so
your body is tired and hungry and that
makes it hard to think or you're really
stressed out and anxious or that was all
kinds of tension in your body so one of
the things we do first there's three
aspects defining your Center it's going
to be centering your posture centering
your tension centering your attitude and
we Center our posture and it's by going
through a particular exercise I want to
explain to you what the purpose of
centering your posture is and what this
exercise is so if I sit just normally
without this is called as a foo a
meditation pillow underneath my body
what happens is because of evolution I
have an s-curve in my spine and I don't
want to hold myself tense right and so
if I relaxed you see what happens I get
a curve in my spine my chest closes in
my stomach closes in and so what I get
is shallow chest breathing and the
problem with shallow chest breathing is
it is very deeply associated in your
brain with anxiety with tension with
distress so you don't want that so you
need what's called your loft and what
that is is you're trying to enact a
basic postural principle the basic
postural principle is you want your
knees level or impossible below your
hips so you need something under your
butt now you can sit two ways I
recommend for people who are initially
sitting you might want to sit this way
cross-legged in front with your knees
down so sit towards the edge of your
pillow and your knees down like this
this is usually easier for beginners
it's not all finally the best posture if
you can and you need to experiment with
your posture and we'll come back to this
towards the end of today's session but
if you can this is actually a preferred
posture for sitting kneeling like this
because what happens when people sit
cross-legged is their hips are usually
slightly lateralized and that puts a bit
of a kink in your hair so if you can sit
this way please do if you have back
problems you can sit in a chair and just
keep your do the exercise with me and
then at the very end of the exercise you
can lean back slightly to take the
pressure off your back or what some
people do in my classes
they go through the centering exercise
and then once they're centered they lean
back slightly against the wall to take
the pressure off their back alright so
what I want to do is show you now that
I'm sitting this way what happens is my
stomach is open my chest is open and my
shoulders are down and that allows
what's called baby breathing now this is
a very important principle unless I give
you specific instructions let your
breathing be as natural as possible
that's how babies breathe how do babies
breathe they do belly breathing they
expand their abdomen you can put your
hands on your abdomen you can feel your
abdomen expanding when you inhale and
exhaling contracting when you exhale try
not to breathe by lifting and dropping
your shoulders okay because that's also
and your aggression tension you want to
be baby breathing because it puts you
into a natural relaxed state but it
doesn't make you sleepy because you're
using most of your lungs and your
abdomen and you're getting lots and lots
of oxygen into your bloat so you want to
do baby breathing so this area is called
your Don Tian let your breathing drop as
low as low as possible don't force it
don't force it into your abdomen and try
to engage in the baby breathing and then
you want your chest open your shoulders
down and you place your hands on your
legs in a way that will do the following
it'll keep your shoulders open right
your chest open your shoulders down and
it will add to your sense of stability
you can place your hands like this some
people put their hands in their lap like
this yeah one thing you do and this is
something I prefer to do my hands sort
of slightly aside like this that works
for me you may find directly palm up
works for you but you can do the chin
mudra you can lightly touch your thumb
you don't have to do this but you can
lightly touch your thumbs to your index
finger and you can feel the pulse there
why that's important is because we're
trying to train two ways of looking in
where you have two eyes sort of looking
inward one is introspection you're very
familiar with that which is looking into
your mind like when I ask you what are
you thinking about right now or to
imagine a sailboat
that's introspection but you also want
interior ception interoception that's
your feeling into your body like if you
if you feel like there's
something's wrong with my stomach or you
know it doesn't feel quite right here in
my chest
that's interception when you do the chin
mudra and you pick up on that pulse and
you can actually enhance your
interception and we're going to talk in
the course while you want to be
enhancing both your introspection and
your interior reception okay
interception okay so you can place your
hands how they're going to be that that
gives you that stability perhaps using
the chin mudra and then we want to avoid
a postural problem with our head which
is people tend to let their head roll
forward especially if they're novices
don't do that because this is sending
the signal to your brain that you want
to fall asleep and we're trying to get
between two things that your brain wants
to do when you close your eyes you look
inward when you close your eyes and
looking with your brain goes oh I know
what you want to do you're daydreaming
and it'll start do all the day driven
and we want to get out of that I mean
and then you when you get out of that
your brain goes oh I know what you want
to do you want to fall asleep and you
want to get out of that you're trying to
steer between those two so you want to
keep your head level alright so what I
want to do now don't do it yet I'm going
to talk you through it so just listen
through the instructions first please
and then I'll talk you through it we're
going to do an exercise in order to find
your Center I don't let you sort of just
use visual cues and Cartesian graph
fashion calculate your Center I want you
to find your Center and this is what
we're going to do again don't do it yet
please watch and listen and then I'll
talk you through it we're going to close
our eyes and we're going to and it's
very important to close your eyes for
this exercise or else you'll rely on
visual cues okay you can close your eyes
you're going to use your middle ears
vestibular function it's 400 million
years old it will send all kinds of
reliable signals to you but you're
balanced okay and you're gonna roll
forward and you're going to feel the
sensations of being off-center forward
and then backwards and you're going to
do that a little less each time slowly
by tracking the sensations slowly
tracking it on where you feel centered
back to front and then you're going to
do the same thing side to side okay
and then in order to make sure we got
our head properly in place given what I
just said a few minutes ago we do our
head back to front and side to side once
we are centered in that way we're going
to sink into our center what that means
is we're going to try and open our leg
and abdomen and chest muscles and our
neck muscles as much as possible we're
not going Lin we're doing it as much so
that we can reliably feel state because
you're probably holding a lot of
unnecessary tension in all of those
muscles
once you sink into your Center I'll say
savor your Center what you're trying to
do here is really like almost like
you're like somebody put some food in
your mouth and you want to really
heighten the sensation of the awareness
oh I want to remember what this feels
like in the same way you want to try to
create a felt memory of what it's like
to be centered okay so everybody start
you know getting into your basic posture
and then close your eyes I'm going to
now talk you through this exercise so
your eyes are closed you're going to
move forward you're feeling off-center
and then slowly backwards feel those
sensations off center and then back and
forth a little less each time slowly
honing in until you feel centered front
to back then side to side
now your head front to back so I decided
make any minor adjustments so head and
body feel Center together now sink into
your center open your stomach muscles
your leg muscles just muscles neck
muscles see if you can find naturally
unforced find your breathing be me your
baby breathing in your abdomen
now savor your Center really savor a try
the creative felt memory so you can find
your way back here again and again what
are the effects on the mind and body of
being centered really taste it deeply
with your mind and body
okay slowly open your eyes please so
whenever we sit we're gonna find your
Center now I've been doing this for
years so I don't have to do that
exercise I can just sit and find my
Center for a long time you want to go
through the exercise until you can find
your Center
so that's centering your posture now
centering your attention obviously it
means to focus your attention but it
means much more I'm going to use an
analogy first of all let me explain the
one part of the analogy think about my
glasses right now how they frame my
experience and I'm seeing through them
in both senses of the word I'm seeing by
means of them and beyond them but I'm
actually not aware of my glasses I'm
aware through them but sometimes my
glasses distort my awareness so what I
have to do is I have to step back and
not look through them step back and look
at them step back and look at them
normally we're not looking at the
process and patterns within our mind and
body we're looking through them out the
world and so what we want to do is we
want to practice stepping back and
looking at our mental framing rather
than automatically and unconsciously
looking through it so how do we do that
well the primary way in which we are
aware of the world is through our
sensation from touching the floor right
now all right so what I want to do is
instead of being aware through my
sensations I want to be aware of my
sensations and the way that I do that as
I pick sensations that are easy to track
because their sensations that are more
touch vision is too fast to start with
so I want to start with sensations of
touch sort of bodily awareness and
something that's always with me which is
the sensations being generated in my
abdomen by my grieving so as I breathe
in I feel those sensations and I
mentally say to myself but mental word
that I'm silently saying to myself is
only a lens I don't concentrate on the
word I use it to focus my attention on
those sensations and I say in and then
out in and then out tracking the change
and flow of the sensations now what will
happen is I'll get distracted it's
called your monkey mind it's like a
monkey that leaps around and chatters
because you go in
to thinking about or sensing the world
so you won't be looking at your mind
you'll be looking through your mind
you'll be thinking about the laundry you
have to do remembering their
conversation you had worrying about a
problem in your life maybe listening to
what's happening in your room or outside
okay so when that happens you're going
to step back and look at the distraction
you're not going to get involved with
the contents let's say you have a
thought don't get involved with that
your thoughts about step back and label
the process remember we're trying to
focus on the process and patterns label
the process with an ING word like
thinking imagining wondering complaining
listening okay don't worry about being
super precise in your labeling
just get you what intuitively comes up
first is more than sufficient
so you label your distraction with an
ING word and then you return your
attention to the sensations and your
breath this is where we bring in the
third thing we're training we train our
attitude and I want to use an excellent
analogy from John cornfield one of the
people who brought the pasta to North
America in the 70s I believe in facts
about your training your monkey mind the
rain your way you're training a puppy
dog to stay so if I have a puppy dog in
front of me and I'm trying to make it
stay you know and it oh oh stay come on
if I do that I will train the puppy dog
to fight and fear me and instead of
befriend in my mind I will make it my
worst enemy the democratic talks about
there is no enemy worse than your own
mind and there is no ally greater than
your own mind you don't want to fight
your puppy dog should I just feed it in
the sense of just letting it do whatever
it wants right oh there oh well oh well
oh well no that won't work either if you
just indulge the puppy dog you won't
train it to pro friend the puppy dog you
have to take that attitude of the you
know the attitude you would take towards
a puppy dog are loving the friend
patience Oh would you go oh there you
are oh okay there you are Oh anywhere oh
there you
and what you have to remember is you
spent a lifetime building up habits of
mind and body and you're putting very
very little time in it in an attention
against it in this practice it's amazing
that it actually works it's like a
gentle rain that can erode the tallest
mountain but it takes time it takes time
now that brings me to a way in which
people frequently miss miss frame
meditation and use it as a justification
for not undertaking the practice they
say to make themselves or to me the
Vatican I can't meditate my mind just
goes off and what they're saying is I'm
not meditating unless my mind is wide
open and empty like some sort of
Canadian Tundra that is too radically
miss frame so there's a metaphor that's
used in tradition that's the like the
person who says I can't get the glass of
water clean the glass of water has got
sort of mud in it and they keep sticking
a fork in and they're trying to force
the mud down and it just won't go cool I
can't do this and that of course they're
doing the wrong thing they're taking the
wrong attitude what you have to realize
is you have to set conditions up so that
your mind will settle clear and that
takes a long time as I've just said the
way to frame this is to realize whenever
you're touching yourself in a
distraction that's a moment of which
Buddha means the awakened one that's a
moment of breaking up and being able to
return to your Center you should not you
should think of those moments of return
as like doing reps in weight training
you're actually building the muscle of
mindfulness then you are really
meditating so take a moment or two
adjust your posture any way you would
like and then what we're going to do is
the following
we're going to go into a fifteen minute
sit and what we need to do for that is
we're going to close our eyes and
there's going to be like a few minutes
where you take on to go to I won't talk
you through at this time but you're
going to go through the centering
exercise your going to Center your
posture and then you're going to Center
your mind
on the sensations in your don.t and
remember don't push your breathing but
find where your sensations are naturally
falling and then follow them naturally
when you're distracted label the
distracting process with an ING word and
then return to your breath centering
your attitude and framing this as all of
those returns are wonderful that means
you are building the muscle of
mindfulness
all right let's now begin enjoy your
city
you
slowly begin to come out have you
practice trying as best you can to
integrate when you cultivated in your
practice with your elevated
consciousness and cognition
please remember meditation is not a
vacation it's an education that you want
to bring into all of your life now let's
talk about some general rules of thumb
for practice
continuity practice is more important
than quantity ideally you want to be
sitting 15 to 20 minutes every day using
a timer don't just sit for as long as
you feel comfortable sitting said but
the timer put yourself into a bit of
childish if you if you honestly can only
sit for five minutes don't say to
yourself all I can't sit for 50 minutes
so it won't sit at all sit for the five
minutes when you sit go through the
centering exercise and then go into
other the pasta meditation don't
meditate right after eating it just
listen to your stomach digesting right
after listening to music it was play
like a tape in your head right after
watching TV show you'll just keep
playing it right after you've had an
emotionally challenging or intense
conversation with somebody positive or
negative because you'll just keep
playing it in your head you want to sit
in a quiet softly
that brings up a couple of important
important points while you're sitting
it's often the case for many people
they'll get very odd experiences you'll
feel like an electric shock go through
you you'll feel very hot or you feel
that cold you feel like you may be
floating or sinking or not on although
you know you're sitting normally you'll
feel contorted this does not mean you're
going insane it also does not mean
you're about to experience enlightenment
to become a Buddha it means neither of
those right it just means areas of the
brain are starting to talk to each other
that have not been normally talking to
each other label those as a distraction
and return now if you've experienced
trauma or in therapy very important that
you talk to therapists and let them know
you're doing this mindfulness properties
if you experience the trauma and you're
not in therapy I would recommend you
consider not undertaking this practice
right now until you get into a stable
therapeutic relationship those are usual
for which that is not the situation
again please treat any of those unusual
experience distractions and return to
your breath but if you meditate in
darkness it'll tend to exacerbate those
odd experiences for you it's a good idea
if you can to practice twice a day but
again be going practice once and then
practice once today you'll be doing that
if when you join me in the sittings
every morning except for Sunday there
won't be any sittings together on Sunday
but I suggest you still sit on your own
on Sunday so I now want to turn to some
questions there were a house last time
in the video that had the technical
problems and I want to address some of
those questions because they're really
good ones before I move on on to some of
the novel questions we might get from
today one question was from Blessed now
is that okay that my legs get strained
when I meditate on my knees well first
of all you as I said experiment with
your posture
you might try crossly that will reduce
the tension but it's very important to
frame that experiment experimentation
properly do you not get it into your
mind that you're going to find the
perfect posture that will remove you
from all feelings of discomfort and that
you will feel sort of loss of sensations
of bullet player
moving through your body that's not
going to happen okay so experiment with
your posture until you get to something
that's relatively good for you but
you're going to get a keenness in your
legs your fun sometimes find achiness
and different parts of your body that is
unavoidable so don't try and frame it
that you're gonna make that go away it's
very possible that your legs will fall
asleep I have never met anybody in the
29 years I've been doing this who's
practiced meditation and in any way
damaged their legs by how their legs
falling asleep now one thing you should
do though is when you come out of your
sick because your legs or your ankle
your feet might be asleep get up very
slowly and gently so you do not twist
your ankle or perhaps fall unnecessarily
my posture also seems to be inhibit
being my focus is as a rotate okay to
lie down to meditate this is from Jordan
McEntire no that's not a good idea if
the problem is as I say back pain then
use the chair method that I've already
described or use the wall method the
problem when you lay down is it can
exacerbate those disorientation feelings
and it can make the weirdness worse or
if it doesn't do that there's a good
chance you will fall asleep and as I
mentioned you're trying to get between
monkey mind and falling asleep it's a
middle path and it's very narrow right
now you're like on the edge of a wedge
and it's gonna open as you move into it
um it's a good idea not to meditate
right before you're going to sleep
because you might fall asleep and your
meditation or you might get fully sort
of awake and present and therefore I'll
reduce your capacity for going to sleep
if you want to meditate in the evening I
suggest like an hour after dinner or so
another question from Spencer if I get
an insight while meditating should I
just labor look like I would any other
monkey mind moment yes exactly and this
the scientific research shows that this
kind of mindfulness practice engenders
insight so but you don't want to get
caught up on it and you have to trust
the fact that that sensitivity and
proclivity towards insight is going to
carry into your daily life if you focus
on it in your meditation then you're not
going to transfer that insight ability
really need it which is into the world
what you can do and some people do is
they keep a journal here and they tell
themselves all you know all right when I
come out of my meditation all write down
any insights I might have don't try and
hold them in your mind for writing let
them go and if you remember them you do
and if you don't you don't and but you
might come back to them it's a good idea
also to perhaps Bailey with horror to
how your meditation practice is going
because it helps to build your awareness
of your inner teacher and the tradition
this is called like watering your Buddha
okay so unfortunately we are out of time
for today I have to get to an online
virtual class normally the Tuesday
classes won't be this long because it
will only be a sit tomorrow will you
will meet at 9:30 and we will do a quick
review of what we did today we will sit
and then they'll be more in Q&A so if I
didn't get to your question today please
save it for tomorrow please remember to
hit the subscribe button and that way
you can get notifications of anything
pertaining to meditation and you can
also be put in touch with other relevant
videos on my channel thank you very much
for your time and attention I'll see you
tomorrow at 9:30 please continue with
your practice